Finding Aid for Minor J. Coon papers, 1946-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Minor J. Coon papers 1946-2004, 1970-1999
Minor J. Coon.
1.25 linear foot
0774 Aa 2
Professor and Chair of the Department of Biological Chemistry at the University of Michigan. Coon was internationally recognized for his pioneering research in P450 enzymes. Papers include topical files containing biographical and professional records, including reviews of the biological chemistry department from 1970-1988, awards, honorary degrees, lectureships, and programs. Also includes photographs that span Coon's 47-year career at the University of Michigan, with a focus on awards received.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (Donor # 9568 ) was received from the creator in March 2005.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Dr. Minor J. ("Jud") Coon was born in 1921 in Englewood, Colorado. He graduated summa cum laude with a B.A. from the University of Colorado in 1943 and went on to do graduate studies at the University of Illinois. Coon received his Ph.D. in 1946 and remained at the University of Illinois to do postdoctoral research for the next year. In 1947 he joined the faculty of the Department of Physiological Chemistry at the University of Pennsylvania, where he undertook studies on amino acid metabolism. Coon stayed at the University of Pennsylvania for several years and was promoted to Assistant Professor in 1949 and Associate Professor in 1953. He moved to the University of Michigan Medical School in 1955 when he was offered a position as Professor in the Department of Biological Chemistry.
While at the University of Michigan, he served as chairman of the Department of Biological Chemistry from 1970 to 1990. In 1983 he was named the Victor C. Vaughan Distinguished University Professor. While chairman, Coon emphasized the importance of teaching, strengthened the graduate program, and recruited outstanding faculty members, many with joint appointments. Coon received recognition for many awards at UM, including the Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award, the Distinguished Faculty Lectureship Award in Biomedical Research, the Henry Russel Lectureship, and the Distinguished Achievement Award of the Medical Center Alumni Society.
Coon's impact on the biochemistry and molecular biology world was large. Coon completed early studies on fatty acid and amino acid metabolism, pioneered research on P450 enzymes, and researched the biosynthesis of steroid hormones and the activation of environmental carcinogens.
In addition to his research, Coon has been active in service to the biochemistry community. National and international awards include the Paul Lewis Award in Enzyme Chemistry by the American Chemical Society, Michigan Scientist of the Year, Bernard Brodie Award in drug metabolism, the first William C. Rose Award from the American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology. Coon was also honored by the National Academy of Sciences, the Institute of Medicine, and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. Coon also served as President of the Association of Medical School Departments of Biochemistry (1974-1975), on the Executive Committee of International Union of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (1985-1991), and President of the American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (1991-1992). Coon was also editor-in-chief of Biochemical Preparations and Microsomes, Drug Oxidations and Chemical Carcinogenesis. Coon has served on the editorial boards of Biochemistry, Molecular Pharmacology, and the Journal of Biological Chemistry.
The Minor J. Coon papers (1.25 linear feet) (1946-2004) document Coon's internationally known career in biological chemistry at the University of Michigan. The Coon papers contain two series, Topical Files and Photographs.
Subjects:
Coon, Minor Jesser, 1921-; Biochemistry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Biological Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Cytochrome P-450.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical Files
  Topical Files (1.25 linear feet) contain biographical and professional information during his 47-year career at the University of Michigan. There is a strong focus on reviews of the Biological Chemistry Department from the time he became Chair in 1970 until 1988. Biographical information can be found in folders containing his bibliography, curriculum vitae, and retirement memoir. Professional information related to his career focuses on Coon's recognition as an internationally known researcher in biochemistry, biophysics, and molecular biology, with a focus on P450 enzymes, which are involved in the metabolism of drugs. Many files relate to Coon's accomplishments in relation to awards, honorary degrees, his appointment as the Victor C. Vaughan Distinguished Professor, and his lectureships. Also included are work and correspondence with his post-doctoral student Anthony Y.H. Lu, programs and invitations to conferences and events in honor of Coon, and writings by and dedicated to Coon.
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Bibliography 2005 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1987-2004 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae 2005 (Box 1)
  - Department of Biological Chemistry
    - Biological Chemistry Department Chairman Summaries 1970-1990 (Box 1)
    - Biological Chemistry Department Periodic Review 1976-1981 (Box 1)
    - Biological Chemistry Department Review 1970-1976 (Box 1)
    - Biological Chemistry Department Review 1981-1988 (Box 1)
    - Report of the External Review of the Department of Biological Chemistry, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Dissertation: The Amino Acid Requirements of Man, 1946 (Box 1)
  - FASEB Satellite Symposium 1991 (Box 1)
  - Henry Russel Lectureship 1991 (Box 1)
  - Honorary Degrees (Box 1)
  - LCME Data, Biological Chemistry 1981 (Box 1)
  - Lu, Anthony Y. H. (Box 1)
  - Minor J. and Mary Lou Coon Graduate Student Fellowship Award (Box 1)
  - News Clippings (Box 1)
  - P450 Conference 2001 (Box 1)
  - Porter, Todd D. (Box 1)
  - Programs, Invitations, Flyers (Box 1)
  - Retirement Memoir 2002 (Box 1)
  - Search and Survey Committee and Coon Appointment 1970 (Box 1)
  - Victor C. Vaughan Distinguished Professorship (Box 2)
  - Writings (Box 2)
- Photographs
  Photographs (1959-2002) (3 packets) contain images of Coon spanning his career. Most photographs are identified by year and by individual. Many photographs are related to Coon receiving awards that are discussed in his papers found in the Topical Files. Other photographs include Coon with his wife, Mary Lou, at conferences and receptions in the United States and abroad, as well as teaching.
  - 1959-2002, 3 packets (Box 2)